A Guide to the Papers of Mary Johnston
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Manuscripts
  - Sir Mortimer- incomplete preliminary draft of the published novel, [1903-1904]; AMs (Box Box 16)
  - Sir Mortimer- published novel, 1903; AMs (Box Box 17)
  - Sir Mortimer- incomplete draft of published novel, 1903; TMs (Box Box 17)
  - Sir Mortimer- published novel, 1903; TMs (Box Box 17)
  - Sir Mortimer- incomplete draft of published novel, 1903; TMs (Box Box 17)
  - Sir Mortimer- published novel, miscellaneous chapters, 1903; TMs (Box Box 17)
  - "That Cold"- published short story, [1928]; TMs (Box Box 18)
  - "Tiger Lady"- unpublished short story, n.d.; TMs (Box Box 18)
  - "Tobacco"- published in Virginian Adventure Series, [1931]; TMs (Box Box 18)
  - "The Travelling Tutor"- unpublished, unfinished short story, n.d.; TMs notes (Box Box 18)
  - "The Tree"- published short story, [1922]; TMs(carbons) (Box Box 18)
  - "The Two Business Men"- published short story, [1928]; TMs (Box Box 18)
  - "The Valentine"- unpublished short story, [1933]; 3 TMs (Box Box 18)
  - "The Voices"- unpublished short story, [1933]; 1 TMs and 2 carbons (Box Box 18)
  - "The Witch and the Magician"- unpublished story, TMs and TMs(carbon) (Box Box 18)
  - "The Woman's War"- published article, [1910]; TMs (Box Box 18)
  - Notebook for Albemarle County, includes sketches entitled "The House on the Shore," and "The Goddess of Reason", ca. 1900-1910; AMs (Box Box 18)
- Adaptations of Mary Johnston's Works
  - Lewis Rand- 1st Act of projected but uncompleted dramatization of Mary Johnstonnovel by Mrs. Cushingham, 1936; TMs (Box Box 19)
  - Prisoners of Hope- Play adapted from Mary Johnston's novel by Ernest F. Boddington and W. L. Lockwood, 1900; TMs (Box Box 19)
  - Prisoners of Hope- Dramatization of Mary Johnston's novel by Ernest F. Boddington and W. L. Lockwood, acts I and II, 1900; TMs (Box Box 19)
  - Prisoners of Hope- Dramatization of Mary Johnston's noveI by Ernest F. Boddington and W. L. Lockwood, acts III and IV, 1900; TMs (Box Box 19)
  - To Have and To Hold- Play, adaptation from Mary Johnston's novel by Ernest F. Boddington, 1902; TMs (Box Box 19)
  - To Have and To Hold- Play, dramatization from Mary Johnston's novel by Ernest F. Boddington, 1902; TMs (Box Box 19)
- Diaries and Biographies
  - Diaries of Mary Johnston, 1906-ca. 1929; 7 volumes (Box Box 20)
  - Copies of Mary Johnston's diary entries; typed by Elizabeth Johnstonfor a future biographer's use, 1906; TMs (Box Box 21)
  - Copies of Mary Johnston's diary entries, 8 folders, 1907-1912; TMs (Box Box 21)
  - Biographical sketches for publishers and the press, 2 TMs w/carbons (Box Box 21)
  - Preliminary rough draft of biography of Mary Johnstonorganized and written by Elizabeth Johnston; unpublished; Book I, Part I - "Childhood" - taken from Mary's unfinished autobiography, 1953; TMs (Box Box 21)
  - Preliminary draft of biography of Mary Johnston; Book I, Part II - "Youth" taken from Mary's unfinished autobiography, 1953; TMs (Box Box 21)
  - Preliminary rough draft of biography of Mary Johnston; Book I, Part III "Maturity" - taken from Mary Johnston's unfinished autobiography, 1953; TMs (Box Box 22)
  - Two later drafts of biography; Book I, Part I, 1953; TMs (Box Box 22)
  - Two later drafts of biography; Book I, Part II, 1953; TMs (Box Box 22)
  - Two later drafts of biography; Book I, Part III, 1953; TMs (Box Box 22)
  - Later draft of biography; Book II, Parts I and II, 1953; TMs (Box Box 22)
  - Miscellaneous drafts later used in biography, n.d.; TMs (Box Box 22)
  - "The World and Mary Johnston" published article by Edward Wagenknecht, 1931; TMs(copies) (Box Box 22)
  - "Mary Johnston - 1870-1936" by Arthur Goodrich, 2 AMsS; TMs(copy); 2 clippings (Box Box 23)
- Johnston Family Papers
  - Genealogical material on the Nash, Bell, Johnston families including typescript copies of wills, obituaries collected by Charles Johnston, 1737-1929 (Box Box 23)
  - Notebook containing genealogical information on the Johnston family, 1875 (Box Box 23)
  - Papers re: Buchanan, Virginia, Mary Johnston's birthplace, n.d.; 8 items (Box Box 23)
  - Scrapbook containing newspaper clippings on John W. Johnston and other Confederateofficers, post-1905 (Box Box 23)
  - Genealogical material re: Johnston family, including two newsclippings of relatives' obituaries written by C. F. Johnston and sketches of John W. Johnston's life (Box Box 23)
  - Newsclippings, postcard re: Three Hills, Mary Johnston's home in Warm Springs, Virginia, n.d. (Box Box 23)
- Accounts
  - American Play Company accounts with Mary Johnston, 1916-1918; 1920-1921; 23 items (Box Box 24)
  - Ernest F. Boddington accounts with Mary Johnston, 1902; 3 items (Box Box 24)
  - Stuart Bowe, Attorney, accounts with Mary Johnston, 1902; 1 item (Box Box 24)
  - Brandt and Kirkpatrick accounts with Mary Johnston, 1920; 2 items (Box Box 24)
  - Brandt and Brandt accounts with Mary Johnston, 1925-1929; 1931-1936; 39 items (Box Box 24)
  - Carl Brandt accounts with Eloise Johnston, 1936-1937; 2 items (Box Box 24)
  - Brandt and Brandt accounts with Elizabeth Johnston, 1958; 1 item (Box Box 24)
  - Archibald Constable and Company accounts with Mary Johnston, 1899-1909; 1911; 1913-1915; 95 items (Box Box 24)
  - Harper and Brothersaccounts with Mary Johnston, 1907-1908;1916; 1922; 9 items (Box Box 24)
  - Houghton, Mifflin and Company accounts with Mary Johnston, 1899-1908;1910-1912; 1914-1917; 1927; 1928; 91 items (Box Box 24)
  - Liebler and Company accounts with Mary Johnston, 1902; 41 items (Box Box 25)
  - Liebler and Company accounts with Mary Johnston and Ernest F. Boddington, 1902; 12 items (Box Box 25)
  - Liebler and Company accounts with Mary Johnston and Harriet Ford, 1902; 6 items (Box Box 25)
  - Liebler and Company accounts with Mary Johnston, 1903-1906; 1908; 1910; ca. 146 items (Box Box 25)
  - Elisabeth Marbury accounts with Mary Johnston, 1900; 2 items (Box Box 25)
  - Elisabeth Marbury accounts with Ernest F. Boddington, 1901; 3 items (Box Box 25)
  - Elisabeth Marbury accounts with Mary Johnston, 1914; 1 item (Box Box 25)
  - Shubert Theatrical Company accounts with Mary Johnston, 1909; 3 items (Box Box 25)
  - Account book, 1899-1905; 1 item (Box Box 25)
  - Miscellaneous financial records of Mary Johnston, 1905; 1912; n.d.; 8 items (Box Box 25)
  - Account book of income of Mary Johnstonfrom her writing; also includes list of books read, letters written, magazine subscriptions, 1913-1937; 1 item (Box Box 25)
- Financial and Legal Papers
  - Cash book of Mary Johnston, 1913-1940; 1 item (Box Box 25)
  - Cash book, 1925-1930; 1 item (Box Box 26)
  - Business Papers re: Mary Johnston's estate, 1936-1940 (Box Box 26)
  - Personal business papers of Elizabeth Johnston, ca. 1955-1958; 14 items (Box Box 26)
  - Archibald Constable and Company- Contract for Audrey, 1901; 1 item (Box Box 26)
  - Liebler and Company- Contract with Mary Johnstonfor Audrey, 1901; ca. 5 items (Box Box 26)
  - Harper and Brothers- Contract for Sir Mortimer, 1902; 2 items (Box Box 26)
  - Archibald Constable and Company- Contract for Sir Mortimer, 1903; 1 item (Box Box 26)
  - Eloise Johnston- Power of Attorney from Mary Johnston, 1905; 1 item (Box Box 26)
  - Houghton Mifflin and Company- Contract for The Goddess of Reason, 1907; 1 item (Box Box 26)
  - Julia Marlowe- Contract for right to produce The Goddess of Reason, 1908; 5 items (Box Box 26)
  - Archibald Constable and Company- Contract for The Long Roll and Cease Firing, 1910; 1 item (Box Box 26)
  - Houghton Mifflin and Company- Contract for The Long Roll, 1911; 1 item (Box Box 26)
  - Archibald Constable and Company- Contract for English edition of Cease Firing, 1911; 1 item (Box Box 26)
  - Houghton Mifflin and Company- Contract for Cease Firing, 1912; 1 item (Box Box 26)
  - Houghton Mifflin and Company- Contract for Hagar, 1913; 1 item (Box Box 26)
  - Houghton Mifflin and Company- Contract for The Witch, 1914; 1 item (Box Box 26)
  - Irving Dittenhoeffer- Assertion of Motion Picture rights to Audrey, 1915; 1 item (Box Box 26)
  - Houghton Mifflin and Company- Contract for The Fortune of Garin, 1915; 1 item (Box Box 26)
  - Irving Dittenhoeffer- Agreement for extension of motion picture production of Audrey, 1916; 1 item (Box Box 26)
  - Harper and Brothers- Contract for Foes, 1918; 1 item (Box Box 26)
  - Butterworth Limited- Contract for English rights to 1492, 1922; 1 item (Box Box 26)
  - Little Brown and Company- Contract for Croatan, 1922; 1 item (Box Box 26)
  - Little Brown and Company- Contract for novel following Croatan, 1924; 1 item (Box Box 26)
  - Butterworth Limited- Contract for English publication of The Slave Ship, 1925; 1 item (Box Box 26)
  - Little Brown and Company- Contract for The Great Valley, 1925; 1 item (Box Box 26)
  - Little Brown and Company- Contract for The Exile, 1926; 1 item (Box Box 26)
  - Little Brown and Company- Contract for re-publishing of four novels, 1926; 1 item (Box Box 26)
  - H. Christiansen- Contract for translation of The Slave Ship into Danish, 1929; 1 item (Box Box 26)
  - Little Brown and Company- Contract for The Hunting Shirt, 1931; 2 items (Box Box 26)
  - Butterworth Limited- Contract for English rights to Hunting Shirt, 1931; 1 item (Box Box 26)
  - Little Brown and Company- Contract for Delicia Allen, 1932; 1 item (Box Box 26)
  - Houghton Mifflin and Company- Contract for "School Edition" of To Have and To Hold, 1933; 1 item (Box Box 26)
  - Butterworth Limited- Contract for Drury Randall, 1935; 1 item (Box Box 26)
  - Caroline Cushingand Eloise Johnston- Contract for the dramatization of Lewis Rand, 1940; 2 items (Box Box 26)
- Photographs and Prints
  - Photographs of Mary Johnston, her friends, family, her travels, 35 items (Box Box 26)
  - Photographs - to be used as illustrations in Mary Johnston's books, n.d.; 5 items (Box Box 26)
  - Miscellaneous prints, 3 of which are etchings, n.d.; 8 items (Box Box 26)
- Speeches
  - Suffrage Speeches, [19l0]; 13 TMs (Box Box 27)
  - Speeches re: Women's Suffrage, eugenics, labor rights for women, [1910-1911]; 11 TMs (Box Box 27)
  - Suffrage speeches, [1910-1911]; 12 TMs (Box Box 27)
  - Fragments, notes, speeches, [1910]; TMs (Box Box 27)
  - Suffrage, labor speeches, [1910-1911]; 23 TMs (Box Box 27)
  - Suffrage speeches, [1910-1912]; 31 TMs (Box Box 27)
  - Notes, fragments, speeches, [1910]; TMs (Box Box 27)
  - "The Character of Lee"- a speech by Mary Johnston, [1932]; TMs (Box Box 27)
  - Speeches re: reading and writing books, [1934]; 10 TMs (Box Box 27)
  - Speech for Confederate Veteransand Kiwanis Club, [1934]; 2 TMs (Box Box 27)
  - "Virginia"- a speech, [1935]; TMs (Box Box 27)
  - Alpha Kamma Gammaspeech, [1935]; 2 TMs (Box Box 27)
  - Women's Suffrage - notes for speeches, n.d.; AMs (Box Box 27)
  - Notes for a travel speech, n.d.; TMs (Box Box 27)
  - Lecture for Women's Suffrage, n.d.; TMs (Box Box 27)
- Miscellaneous
  - Scrapbook consisting of famous quotations written in the hands of Mary Johnston's friends, including Ellen Glasgowand Walter Hines Page, 1 item (Box Box 28)
  - Miscellaneous notes, quotations in author's hand (Box Box 28)
  - Notebook containing French, miscellaneous notes, n.d.; 1 item (Box Box 28)
  - Miscellaneous personal items, n.d.; 21 items (Box Box 28)
  - Notes on "texture" in unidentified hand, 1 item (Box Box 28)
  - Items commemorating the death of Mary Johnston, 1936; ca. 18 items (Box Box 28)
- Clippings and Printed Material
  - Newspapers re: end of WWII, 1945 May 8; 3 items (Box Box 28)
  - Printed material, 1922; 1929; 1936; 1946; n.d.; 7 items (Box Box 28)
  - Newspapers collected by John W. Johnston, 1847-1877; ca. 20 items (Box Box 29)
  - Clippings, pamphlets re: peace movement, amnesty, Socialist Party, 1913-1920; ca. 20 items (Box Box 29)
  - Clippings re: Women's Suffrage, 1909-1920; ca. 50 items (Box Box 29)
  - Clippings re: Women's Suffrage and Mary Johnston, 1909-1911; 25 items (Box Box 29)
  - Clippings re: Women's Suffrage, collected by Mary Johnston, 1911-1913; 42 items (Box Box 29)
  - Clippings re: Co-education at University of Virginia, 1912; 6 items (Box Box 29)
  - Clippings re: Women's Suffrage and Mary Johnston, 1912-1914; 66 items (Box Box 29)
  - Woman's Suffrage Award - Honor Roll Member National American Woman Suffrage Association, 1920; 1 item (Box Box 30)
  - Clippings re: Women's Suffrage; collected by Mary Johnston, n.d.; 81 items (Box Box 30)
  - Printed matter - "Women's Hour" by Charlotte Perkins Gilman, n.d.; 1 item (Box Box 30)
  - Clippings re: Women's Suffrage and Mary Johnston, 13 items (Box Box 30)
  - Printed matter - Women's Suffrage pamphlets collected by Mary Johnston, n.d.; ca. 10 items (Box Box 30)
  - Printed matter - Women's Suffrage pamphlets collected by Mary Johnston, n.d.; ca. 30 items (Box Box 30)
  - Printed matter re: Women's Suffrage, n.d.; ca. 30 items (Box Box 30)
  - Printed matter - Critical and descriptive articles re: Mary Johnston's novels, 6 items (Box Box 30)
  - Clippings re: Prisoners of Hope, 1898; 4 items (Box Box 30)
  - Clippings re: To Have and To Hold, 1900; 1955; 87 items (Box Box 30)
  - Clippings re: Sir Mortimer, 1904; 170 items (Box Box 30)
  - Clippings re: Lewis Rand, 1908; 200 items (Box Box 31)
  - Clippings and programs re: Goddess of Reason, a play, 1909; 33 items (Box Box 31)
  - Clippings re: Cease Firing, 1912; 10 items (Box Box 31)
  - Clippings re: The Long Roll, 1912; 62 items (Box Box 31)
  - Clippings re: Hagar, 1913; 244 items (Box Box 31)
  - Clippings re: Hagar, 1913; l00 items (Box Box 32)
  - Clippings re: The Witch, 1914; ca. 255 items (Box Box 32)
  - Clippings re: The Fortunes of Garin, 1915; 133 items (Box Box 32)
  - Clippings re: The Wanderers, 1917; 12 items (Box Box 32)
  - Clippings re: Michael Forth, 1920; 8 items (Box Box 32)
  - Clippings re: 1492, 1922; 28 items (Box Box 32)
  - Clipping re: Sweet Rocket, 1925; 1 item (Box Box 32)
  - Printed matter - Miscellaneous pamphlets, n.d.; ca. 15 items (Box Box 32)
  - Miscellaneous topics of interest to Mary Johnston, n.d.; ca. 45 items (Box Box 32)
- Oversize Items
  - Ledger book containing notes from Bible records and genealogical charts on the Johnston family, 1 item